Nobody has gone through systematically to work out which molecules really are pheromones. They've just plucked a few, and all these experiments are based on those, but there's no good evidence at all. Now, that's not to say that smell is not important to people. It is, and some people are real enthusiasts, and one of these was Napoleon. And famously, you may remember that out on the campaign trail for war, he wrote to his lover, Empress Josephine, saying, "Don't wash. I'm coming home." (Laughter) So he didn't want to lose any of her richness in the days before he'd get home, and it is still, you'll find websites that offer this as a major quirk. At the same time, though, we spend about as much money taking the smells off us as putting them back on in perfumes, and perfumes are a multi-billion-dollar business. So what I want to do in the rest of this talk is tell you about what pheromones really are, tell you why I think we would expect humans to have pheromones, tell you about some of the confusions in pheromones, and then finally, I want to end with a promising avenue which shows us the way we ought to be going. So the ancient Greeks knew that dogs sent invisible signals between each other. A female dog in heat sent an invisible signal to male dogs for miles around, and it wasn't a sound, it was a smell. You could take the smell from the female dog, and the dogs would chase the cloth. But the problem for everybody who could see this effect was that you couldn't identify the molecules. You couldn't demonstrate it was chemical. The reason for that, of course, is that each of these animals produces tiny quantities, and in the case of the dog, males dogs can smell it, but we can't smell it. And it was only in 1959 that a German team, after spending 20 years in search of these molecules, discovered, identified, the first pheromone, and this was the sex pheromone of a silk moth. Now, this was an inspired choice by Adolf Butenandt and his team, because he needed half a million moths to get enough material to do the chemical analysis. But he created the model for how you should go about pheromone analysis. He basically went through systematically, showing that only the molecule in question was the one that stimulated the males, not all the others. He analyzed it very carefully. He synthesized the molecule, and then tried the synthesized molecule on the males and got them to respond and showed it was, indeed, that molecule. That's closing the circle. That's the thing which has never been done with humans: nothing systematic, no real demonstration. With that new concept, we needed a new word, and that was the word "pheromone," and it's basically transferred excitement, transferred between individuals, and since 1959, pheromones have been found right the way across the animal kingdom, in male animals, in female animals. It works just as well underwater for goldfish and lobsters. And almost every mammal you can think of has had a pheromone identified, and of course, an enormous number of insects. So we know that pheromones exist right the way across the animal kingdom. What about humans? Well, the first thing, of course, is that we're mammals, and mammals are smelly. As any dog owner can tell you, we smell, they smell. But the real reason we might think that humans have pheromones is the change that occurs as we grow up. The smell of a room of teenagers is quite different from the smell of a room of small children. What's changed? And of course, it's puberty. Along with the pubic hair and the hair in the armpits, new glands start to secrete in those places, and that's what's making the change in smell. If we were any other kind of mammal, or any other kind of animal, we would say, "That must be something to do with pheromones," and we'd start looking properly. But there are some problems, and this is why, I think, people have not looked for pheromones so effectively in humans. There are, indeed, problems. And the first of these is perhaps surprising. It's all about culture. Now moths don't learn a lot about what is good to smell, but humans do, and up to the age of about four, any smell, no matter how rancid, is simply interesting. And I understand that the major role of parents is to stop kids putting their fingers in poo, because it's always something nice to smell. But gradually we learn what's not good, and one of the things we learn at the same time as what is not good is what is good. Now, the cheese behind me is a British, if not an English, delicacy. It's ripe blue Stilton. Liking it is incomprehensible to people from other countries. Every culture has its own special food and national delicacy. If you were to come from Iceland, your national dish is deep rotted shark. Now, all of these things are acquired tastes, but they form almost a badge of identity. You're part of the in-group. The second thing is the sense of smell. Each of us has a unique odor world, in the sense that what we smell, we each smell a completely different world. Now, smell was the hardest of the senses to crack, and the Nobel Prize awarded to Richard Axel and Linda Buck was only awarded in 2004 for their discovery of how smell works. It's really hard, but in essence, nerves from the brain go up into the nose and on these nerves exposed in the nose to the outside air are receptors, and odor molecules coming in on a sniff interact with these receptors, and if they bond, they send the nerve a signal which goes back into the brain. We don't just have one kind of receptor. If you're a human, you have about 400 different kinds of receptors, and the brain knows what you're smelling because of the combination of receptors and nerve cells that they trigger, sending messages up to the brain in a combinatorial fashion. But it's a bit more complicated, because each of those 400 comes in various variants, and depending which variant you have, you might smell coriander, or cilantro, that herb, either as something delicious and savory or something like soap. So we each have an individual world of smell, and that complicates anything when we're studying smell. Well, we really ought to talk about armpits, and I have to say that I do have particularly good ones. Now, I'm not going to share them with you, but this is the place that most people have looked for pheromones. There is one good reason, which is, the great apes have armpits as their unique characteristic. The other primates have scent glands in other parts of the body. The great apes have these armpits full of secretory glands producing smells all the time, enormous numbers of molecules. When they're secreted from the glands, the molecules are odorless. They have no smell at all, and it's only the wonderful bacteria growing on the rainforest of hair that actually produces the smells that we know and love. And so incidentally, if you want to reduce the amount of smell, clear-cutting your armpits is a very effective way of reducing the habitat for bacteria, and you'll find they remain less smelly for much longer. But although we've focused on armpits, I think it's partly because they're the least embarrassing place to go and ask people for samples. There is actually another reason why we might not be looking for a universal sex pheromone there, and that's because 20 percent of the world's population doesn't have smelly armpits like me. And these are people from China, Japan, Korea, and other parts of northeast Asia. They simply don't secrete those odorless precursors that the bacteria love to use to produce the smells that in an ethnocentric way we always thought of as characteristic of armpits. So it doesn't apply to 20 percent of the world. So what should we be doing in our search for human pheromones? I'm fairly convinced that we do have them. We're mammals, like everybody else who's a mammal, and we probably do have them. But what I think we should do is go right back to the beginning, and basically look all over the body. No matter how embarrassing, we need to search and go for the first time where no one else has dared tread. It's going to be difficult, it's going to be embarrassing, but we need to look. We also need to go back to the ideas that Butenandt used when he was studying the silk moth. We need to go back and look systematically at all the molecules that are being produced, and work out which ones are really involved. It isn't good enough simply to pluck a couple and say, "They'll do." We have to actually demonstrate that they really have the effects we claim. There is one team that I'm actually very impressed by. They're in France, and their previous success was identifying the rabbit mammary pheromone. They've turned their attention now to human babies and mothers. So this is a baby having a drink of milk from its mother's breast. Her nipple is completely hidden by the baby's head, but what you'll notice is a white droplet with an arrow pointing to it, and that's the secretion from the areolar glands. Now, we all have them, men and women, and these are the little bumps around the nipple, and if you're a lactating woman, these start to secrete. It's a very interesting secretion. What Benoist Schaal and his team developed was a simple test to investigate what the effect of this secretion might be, in effect, a simple bioassay. So this is a sleeping baby, and under its nose, we've put a clean glass rod. The baby remains sleeping, showing no interest at all. But if we go to any mother who is secreting from the areolar glands, so it's not about recognition, it can be from any mother, if we take the secretion and now put it under the baby's nose, we get a very different reaction. It's a connoisseur's reaction of delight, and it opens its mouth and sticks out its tongue and starts to suck. Now, since this is from any mother, it could really be a pheromone. It's not about individual recognition. Any mother will do. Now, why is this important, apart from being simply very interesting? It's because women vary in the number of areolar glands that they have, and there is a correlation between the ease with which babies start to suckle and the number of areolar glands she has. It appears that the more secretions she's got, the more likely the baby is to suckle quickly. If you're a mammal, the most dangerous time in life is the first few hours after birth. You have to get that first drink of milk, and if you don't get it, you won't survive. You'll be dead. Since many babies actually find it difficult to take that first meal, because they're not getting the right stimulus, if we could identify what that molecule was, and the French team are being very cautious, but if we could identify the molecule, synthesize it, it would then mean premature babies would be more likely to suckle, and every baby would have a better chance of survival. So what I want to argue is this is one example of where a systematic, really scientific approach can actually bring you a real understanding of pheromones. There could be all sorts of medical interventions. There could be all sorts of things that humans are doing with pheromones that we simply don't know at the moment. What we need to remember is pheromones are not just about sex. They're about all sorts of things to do with a mammal's life. So do go forward and do search for more. There's lots to find. Thank you very much. (Applause)
Nadie ha estudiado sistemáticamente para saber qué moléculas son verdaderamente feromonas. Solo han investigado algunas, y todos estos experimentos se basan en ellas, pero no hay ninguna evidencia confiable en absoluto. Eso no quiere decir que el olor no sea importante para la gente. Lo es, y algunas personas son verdaderos entusiastas, y uno de ellos fue Napoleón. Tal vez recordarán, que estando fuera preparándose para la guerra, le escribió a su amante, la emperatriz Josefina, diciendo: "No te bañes. Regreso a casa". (Risas) No quería que ella perdiera su fragancia mientras él regresaba. Al día de hoy, encontrarán sitios web que ofrecen esto como gran excentricidad. Aunque, al mismo tiempo, gastamos casi la misma cantidad de dinero para quitarnos los olores y para ponérnoslos otra vez en perfumes, y los perfumes son un negocio de miles de millones de dólares. Así que lo que haré en el resto de esta charla es decirles qué son realmente las feromonas, decirles por qué suponemos que los humanos tienen feromonas, contarles algunas de las confusiones entorno a las feromonas, y, finalmente, quisiera terminar con una vía prometedora que nos muestra el camino que deberíamos de seguir. Los antiguos griegos sabían que los perros se enviaban señales invisibles unos a otros. Una hembra en celo enviaba una señal invisible a los perros en kilómetros a la redonda, y no era un sonido, era un olor. Podían tomar el olor de la hembra, y los perros perseguían el trapo. Pero el problema para todos quienes podían ver este efecto era que no podían identificar las moléculas. No podían demostrar que era químico. La razón de eso, por supuesto, es que cada uno de estos animales produce cantidades pequeñas, y en el caso del perro, los perros machos pueden olerlo, pero nosotros no. Y fue hasta 1959 que un equipo alemán, después de pasar 20 años en la búsqueda de estas moléculas, descubrió e identificó a la primera feromona, la feromona sexual de la polilla de la seda. Fue una elección increíble de Adolf Butenandt y su equipo, porque necesitó medio millón de polillas para conseguir suficiente material para el análisis químico. Pero él creó el modelo de cómo llevar a cabo el análisis de las feromonas. Básicamente lo hizo de forma sistemática, demostrando que solo la molécula en cuestión era la que estimulaba a los machos, no todas las demás. La analizó cuidadosamente. Sintetizó la molécula, y luego probó la molécula sintetizada en los machos y consiguió que estos respondieran demostrando que era, en efecto, esa molécula. Eso cierra el círculo. Es algo que nunca se ha hecho con humanos, nada sistemático, ninguna demostración real. Con ese nuevo concepto, necesitábamos una nueva palabra, que fue la palabra "feromona", y básicamente, es "emoción transmitida", transmitida entre individuos, y desde 1959, se han encontrado feromonas en todo el reino animal, tanto en machos como en hembras. Igualmente aplica bajo el agua para peces y langostas. Y en casi todos los mamíferos, se ha identificado una feromona, al igual que en un enorme número de insectos. Así que, sabemos que las feromonas existen en todo el reino animal. Pero ¿qué pasa con los seres humanos? Bueno, lo primero, es que somos mamíferos, y los mamíferos son olorosos. Cualquier dueño de un perro puede decir que tanto nosotros como ellos olemos. Pero la verdadera razón por la que podríamos pensar que los seres humanos tienen feromonas es debido al cambio que ocurre a medida que crecemos. El olor en la habitación de un adolescente es muy diferente al olor en la habitación de un niño pequeño. ¿Qué ha cambiado? Por supuesto, es la pubertad. Junto con el vello púbico y el vello en las axilas, nuevas glándulas comienzan a secretar en esos lugares, y eso es lo que ocasiona el cambio en el olor. Si fuéramos otro tipo de mamífero, u otro tipo de animal, diríamos, "Debe tener algo que ver con las feromonas" y empezaríamos a buscar adecuadamente. Pero hay algunos problemas, y es por eso, que pienso que, la gente no ha buscado las feromonas de manera eficaz en los humanos. Efectivamente, hay problemas. Y el primero de ellos quizás es sorprendente. Es cuestión de cultura. Las polillas no entienden mucho sobre lo que es bueno para oler, pero los humanos sí lo hacen, y hasta la edad de casi 4 años, cualquier olor, no importa cuán rancio sea, es simplemente interesante. Y entiendo que el principal papel de los padres es evitar que los niños metan los dedos en el popó, ya que siempre es algo bueno de oler. Pero gradualmente aprendemos lo que no es bueno, y una de las cosas que aprendemos al mismo tiempo es lo que es bueno. El queso detrás de mí es británico, una delicadeza inglesa. Es un Stilton azul maduro. Este gusto es incomprensible para personas de otros países. Cada cultura tiene su propia comida especial y su especialidad nacional. Si vinieran de Islandia, su platillo nacional sería tiburón podrido. Todos estos son gustos adquiridos, pero forman casi un signo de identidad. Eres parte del grupo. En segundo lugar esta el sentido del olfato. Cada uno de nosotros tiene un mundo de olores único, en el sentido de que cuando olemos, cada uno huele un mundo completamente diferente. El olfato fue el más difícil de los sentidos de descifrar, y el Premio Nobel otorgado a Richard Axel y Linda Buck en 2004, fue por descubrir cómo funciona el sentido del olfato. Es verdaderamente difícil, pero en esencia, los nervios del cerebro se dirigen a la nariz y sobre estos nervios expuestos al aire exterior se encuentran los receptores, y las moléculas de olor que entran con la inhalación interactúan con estos receptores, y si se unen, envían una señal al nervio que regresa hacia el cerebro. No solo tenemos un tipo de receptor. Si eres un ser humano, tienes cerca de 400 diferentes tipos de receptores, y el cerebro sabe lo que estás oliendo debido a la combinación de receptores y a las células nerviosas que estos activan, mandando mensajes hacia el cerebro de forma combinatoria. Pero es un poco más complicado, porque cada uno de esos 400 viene en diversas variantes, y dependiendo de la variante que tengan, pueden oler el cilantro, esa hierba, ya sea como algo delicioso y sabroso o les puede oler a jabón. Así cada uno de nosotros tiene un mundo individual de olores, y eso lo complica todo al estudiar el olfato. Realmente deberíamos hablar de las axilas, y debo decir que tengo particularmente unas muy buenas. No voy a mostrárselas, pero este es el lugar en el que la mayoría de las personas ha buscado las feromonas. Hay una buena razón, que es, que los grandes simios tienen las axilas como su característica única. Los otros primates tienen glándulas de olor en otras partes del cuerpo. Los grandes simios tienen estas axilas llenas de glándulas secretoras produciendo olores todo el tiempo, un enorme número de moléculas. Cuando son secretadas desde las glándulas, las moléculas son inodoras. No tienen ningún olor, y es solo por las maravillosas bacterias que crecen en esta selva de pelo, que se producen los olores que conocemos y amamos. Y si de paso, quieren reducir la cantidad de olor, depilen sus axilas es una forma muy efectiva de reducir el hábitat de las bacterias, y descubrirán que permanecen sin tanto olor por mucho más tiempo. Pero, aunque nos hemos enfocado en las axilas, creo que es en parte porque es el lugar menos vergonzoso para pedir muestras de la gente. En realidad, hay otra razón por la que tal vez no busquemos ahí una feromona sexual universal, y es porque el 20 % de la población mundial no tiene las axilas olorosas como las mías. Y son las personas procedentes de China, Japón, Corea y otras partes del noreste de Asia. Simplemente no segregan los precursores inodoros que las bacterias aman usar para producir los olores que de manera etnocéntrica siempre pensamos que es una característica de las axilas. Por lo tanto, no aplica al 20 % del mundo. Entonces, ¿qué debemos hacer en nuestra búsqueda de las feromonas humanas? Estoy convencido de que las tenemos. Somos mamíferos, y como cualquier otro mamífero, probablemente las tenemos. Pero lo que creo que debemos hacer es regresar al principio, y, básicamente, buscar en todo el cuerpo. No importa qué tan vergonzoso sea, tenemos que buscar e ir por primera vez a donde nadie se ha atrevido Va a ser difícil, va a ser vergonzoso, pero tenemos que buscar. También necesitamos volver a las ideas que usó Butenandt cuando estudió a la polilla de la seda. Necesitamos regresar y examinar sistemáticamente todas las moléculas que se están produciendo, e identificar las que están realmente involucradas. No es suficiente simplemente con tomar un par y decir: "Son estas". Tenemos que demostrar que realmente tienen los efectos que afirmamos. Hay un equipo que me tiene realmente impresionado. Están en Francia, y su éxito anterior fue la identificación de la feromona mamaria del conejo. Tienen su atención ahora en los bebés humanos y en las madres. Este es un bebé tomando leche del pecho de su madre. Su pezón está completamente escondido por la cabeza del bebé, pero lo que notarán es una gotita blanca señalada por una flecha, y es la secreción de las glándulas areolares. Todos las tenemos, hombres y mujeres, son las pequeñas protuberancias alrededor del pezón, y si eres una mujer amamantando, estas comienzan a secretar. Es una secreción muy interesante. Lo qué Benoist Schaal y su equipo desarrollaron fue una prueba sencilla para investigar el efecto de esta secreción, una simple prueba biológica. Este es un bebé durmiendo, y bajo su nariz, pusimos una varilla de vidrio limpio. El bebé permanece dormido, sin mostrar ningún interés en absoluto. Pero si vamos con cualquier madre que este secretando de las glándulas areolares, no se trata de reconocer, puede ser de cualquier madre, si tomamos la secreción y la ponemos debajo de la nariz del bebé, obtenemos una reacción muy diferente. Es la reacción de un conocedor del placer, abre su boca, saca la lengua y comienza a succionar. Ya que viene de cualquier madre, podría en verdad ser una feromona. No se trata de reconocimiento individual. Cualquier madre lo podría hacer. ¿Por qué es importante, aparte de ser muy interesante? Es porque las mujeres varían en el número de las glándulas areolares que tienen, y hay una correlación entre la facilidad con la que los bebés comienzan a succionar y el número de glándulas areolares que tienen. Parece que mientras más secreciones tiene, es probable que el bebe comience a succionar más rápidamente. Si eres un mamífero, el momento más peligroso en la vida son las primeras horas después de nacer. Es necesario esa primera leche, y si no la consigues, no sobrevivirás. Morirás. Debido a que a muchos bebés les resulta difícil tomar esa primera comida, porque no reciben el estímulo adecuado, si pudiéramos identificar cuál era esa molécula, y el equipo francés está siendo muy cuidadoso, pero si pudiéramos identificar la molécula, sintetizarla, entonces significaría que los bebés prematuros tendrían más posibilidades de amamantarse, y cada bebé tendría una mayor oportunidad de sobrevivir. Lo que quiero decir es que este es un ejemplo de cómo un enfoque sistemático, realmente científico, nos puede mostrar una comprensión real de las feromonas. Puede haber todo tipo de intervenciones médicas. Podría haber muchas cosas que los humanos están haciendo con las feromonas que simplemente no sabemos. Lo que debemos recordar es que las feromonas no solo tienen que ver con el sexo. Se relacionan con muchas más cosas en la vida de los mamíferos. Así que adelante y a buscar más. Hay mucho que encontrar. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)